As we learned in our audio drama,
劇形式の聖書朗読でも学んだように
the Jews returned to Jerusalem
ユダヤ人は神殿再建のため
to rebuild the temple in 537 B.C.E.
紀元前537年に
エルサレムに戻ります
And by 515 B.C.E., it was finally completed.
そして紀元前515年
ついに神殿は完成します
However, the city’s walls were still left in ruins.
しかし 城壁は崩れたままでした
エホバが城壁を建て直す
ご予定の時が来ました
Jehovah’s time had now come to rebuild the walls,
and he used the faithful man Nehemiah
エホバは このプロジェクトの
中心人物として
to take the lead in this work.
忠実な人ネヘミヤを選びます
This would be a massive undertaking for the Jews.
これはユダヤ人にとっては
大きな仕事でした
And once again, there were opposers.
しかも 工事を妨害する敵もいたのです
Nehemiah told the nation of Israel
ネヘミヤはイスラエル国民に
that “the joy of Jehovah is your stronghold.”
「エホバからの喜びは皆さんの
力となるのです」と語りました
How could he encourage them to be joyful
反対の中でも喜べるよう
どうやって励ましたのでしょうか
despite all the opposition?
What lessons can we learn from their example?
この出来事からどんな教訓を
学べると思いますか
There are many,
たくさんありますが 今回は
3つの点に注目しましょう
but here are three to think about as you watch:
What role did prayer play in helping Nehemiah
祈りは ネヘミヤが
勇気をもって仕事を行う上で
to be a courageous person for Jehovah?
どんな役割を果たすでしょうか
In addition to direct attacks,
敵は正面攻撃だけでなく
what schemes did the enemies employ
どんな手段を用いてこのプロジェクトを
妨害してくるでしょうか
to oppose the work?
Despite setbacks,
妨害にも負けず ネヘミヤが
喜びを保てたのはどうしてでしょうか
what was Nehemiah’s main source of joy?
Got it?
では これらの点を考えながら
All right, then, with that in mind, please sit back
どうぞ映画をお楽しみください
and enjoy the following video presentation
「エホバからの喜びは力となる」
“The Joy of Jehovah Is Your Stronghold.”
It was a privilege to have a share
エルサレムでのエホバの崇拝の
回復に携われたことは
in the restoration of Jehovah’s worship.
とても名誉なことでした
People know we rebuilt the wall,
城壁再建の話は有名ですが
再建に絡んで
いろんな出来事がありました
but there is so much more to the story.
Let’s start at the beginning.
最初からお話ししましょう
In the 20th year of King Artaxerxes Longimanus,
ペルシャの王 アルタクセルクセス・
ロンギマヌスの第20年
私はシュシャンの宮殿にいました
I was in Shushan the palace.
王の献酌人として仕えていたのです
I was cupbearer to the king.
王は私のことを心から
信頼してくれていました
He trusted me with his life.
でも私としては
Although I was far from Jerusalem,
遠くエルサレムでエホバに仕えている
人たちのことを考えているときが
I found great joy just thinking
about our people there serving Jehovah
一番幸せでした
—until one day when I received a visit
しかしある日 弟のハナニが訪ねて来て
from my brother Hanani.
私の人生は大きく変わることになります
That visit changed everything.
What’s going on, Hanani?
エルサレムはどう？
How are our people?
みんな元気？
Not good.
いやあ
The conditions are disgraceful.
とても大変なことになっています
The walls of Jerusalem are broken down,
エルサレムの城壁は破壊されたままで
and its gates have been burned with fire.
門も焼かれたままなんだ
神殿は？
What about the temple?
It stands,
あるよ でもきちんとした
奉仕は行われていない
but the services are nothing but empty rituals.
祭司たちでさえ神の律法を守ってない
Most of the people and the priests ignore God’s Law.
一緒にエルサレムに戻ってよ
You have to return with us.
For days, my conscience plagued me.
何日もそのことばかり考えていました
Would the king even allow me to go?
王は行かせてくれるだろうか
Our people had sinned
民はエホバの命令を守らず
罪を犯している
by not keeping Jehovah’s commandments,
でも その彼らのために何もしないなら
but now I felt as if I were sinning
自分も罪を犯すことになるのではないか
by not helping them in their time of need.
I begged Jehovah to grant me success.
エホバに導きを求めました
ネヘミヤ
Nehemiah,
why are you so gloomy when you’re not sick?
浮かない顔をしてどうしたんだ
This can be nothing but gloominess of heart.
気になることでもあるのか
Why should I not look gloomy
申し訳ありません
when the city,
父祖たちの故郷 エルサレムが荒れ果て
the place where my forefathers are buried,
門も焼け落ちてしまっている
と聞いたので・・・
lies in ruins,
and its gates have been consumed by fire?
Nehemiah, what is this?
そうだったのか・・・
それでおまえはどうしたいと
思っているんだ？
Speak frankly.
What are you seeking?
At once, I prayed to the God of the heavens.
すぐに天の父に祈りました
もし私が
If it pleases the king
and if your servant has found favor with you,
王の好意を得ており
王が良いと思われるのでしたら
send me to Judah,
to the city where my forefathers are buried,
私をユダに行かせ
そこを再建させてください
and let me rebuild it.
You may go.
行きなさい
エホバは祈りに答えてくださいました
Jehovah was with us.
王は物資や兵士を与えてくれました
The king gave me supplies,
an army,
そして 私を総督として任命したのです
and an appointment as governor.
こうして私たちは エルサレムの
城壁再建のために出掛けました
We were on our way to help rebuild Jerusalem’s walls.
まず少し町を見て回りました
I had seen a portion of the city,
but it wasn’t until I rose
そして 夜に城壁を見に行って初めて
by night to inspect the walls
この町がどれほどひどい扱いを
受けてきたかを知ることになります
that I saw just how badly God’s city had been treated.
待ってて
Wait here.
I couldn’t believe the destruction.
もう信じられませんでした
エルサレムに対するエホバの目的を
思い出させる必要がありました
The time had come
to reveal Jehovah’s purpose for Jerusalem.
それで町の有力者たちに
集まってもらいました
I gathered the leaders.
Who is this man?
あれは誰だ？
I’m told he’s Nehemiah, cupbearer to the king.
ネヘミヤ・・・ 王の献酌人らしいです
何をするつもりだ？
What does he want from us?
Men!
皆さん！
The holy city is completely vulnerable.
聖なる都市エルサレムは
荒れ果てています
Let us rebuild the walls of Jerusalem,
城壁を建て直して
これまでの屈辱を晴らしましょう
so that this disgrace will not continue.
周りの民族はどう思うだろう？
But what will our neighbors think?
強力な敵たちに囲まれているんだぞ
Yes, we have many powerful enemies.
アルタクセルクセス王は
Artaxerxes commissioned me
エルサレムを建て直すことを
私に命じました
to rebuild the walls and the entire city.
Didn’t you see the horsemen he sent
王が遣わした兵士や資材を
皆さんはご覧になったはずです
and all the timber?
He gave it all!
Brothers, the good hand of our God was upon me.
兄弟たち エホバ神の助けは
明らかです！
He is the one to fear, not men.
人ではなく神を畏れましょう
He will give us success.
神は必ず成功させてくださいます
私たちがイスラエルの
人々のために働くことを
Not everyone was happy
that we had come to do something good
みんなが喜んだわけでは
ありませんでした
for the people of Israel.
ネヘミヤの魂胆は分かっている
So that’s what this Nehemiah is up to.
Geshem, do you see what I’m seeing?
ゲシェム どう思う？
Without a wall,
城壁が無ければ
we can keep the Jews under control.
やつらはこちらの言いなりです
If they rebuild it,
でも 城壁ができてしまえば
そうはいきません
the Jews won’t need our land or resources.
歯向かうつもりです
That means he’s planning to rebel.
We can’t let him.
そうはさせん
今すぐやめさせてやる
We must act, and act together.
手を貸してくれ いいな
Are you with me?
You have my support.
もちろんです
And mine, as always.
放ってはおけないでしょう
Good!
エルサレムに行こう
ネヘミヤから目を離すな
We must go to Jerusalem to keep an eye on Nehemiah.
The opposers wanted to maintain control
敵対者たちは 優位に立って
エホバの民から利益を
得たいと考えていました
and to profit from Jehovah’s people.
They wasted little time trying to intimidate us.
それで すぐに圧力をかけてきたのです
あれは誰だ？
Who are these?
あれがサマリアの総督 サンバラテ
That’s Sanballat, governor of Samaria.
横にいるのがトビヤ
Next to him is Tobiah, an Ammonite official
アンモン人の役人で大地主
多くのユダヤ人から支持されてる
and landowner to many of our people.
They all look up to him.
That’s Geshem;
そして ゲシェム
裕福なアラビア人で
he’s a very wealthy Arabian and close ally to Sanballat.
いつも サンバラテと一緒にいる
Nehemiah, are you rebelling against the king?
ネヘミヤ あなたはペルシャの
王に逆らうのですか？
The king himself gave us the authority.
これは王からの命令です
To rebuild the city and the wall?
城壁を修復することが？
To rebuild the city and the wall
そのことを王は望んでいます
is what the king expects us to do.
Why did you not consult with me?
サマリアの総督である私に
何の相談もなく？
I am the governor of Samaria.
Well, yes, but the king appointed
王はこのネヘミヤを
ユダの総督に任命したんです
Nehemiah as governor of Judah.
じゃあ なぜ知らせてこないのですか
われわれもエホバを崇拝しています
So why have you not asked for our help?
We worship Jehovah too.
We’ve sacrificed to him for generations.
ずっとエホバに犠牲を捧げています
Along with sacrifices to all of your other gods.
エホバ以外の神々にも・・・
The God of the heavens
天の神が必ず成功させてくださいます
is the One that will grant us success,
and we, his servants,
それで私たちは建設に取り掛かります
will get up and build.
No one should let his religious beliefs
崇拝よりも われわれが
団結することのほうが大事だろう
come before national unity.
You have neither share
あなた方は エルサレムに
nor claim nor memorial in Jerusalem.
何の権利もありません
Sanballat,
サンバラテ
could it be you
至高の王に逆らうつもりではないですね
who is rebelling against the highest King of all?
Despite opposition,
反対の中でも みんな
頑張って働きました
the people worked strenuously.
ネヘミヤ あれ・・・
Nehemiah, these things have to go somewhere.
大変だったのは城壁の
再建だけではありません
Their struggles went far beyond building a wall.
経済的な問題もありました
Jehovah remembers brothers like Peleth.
エホバはそのこともご存じでした
Seeing how he dealt with personal challenges
ペレトのような 頑張っている
兄弟たちから励まされました
strengthened my faith.
ペレト
Peleth.
ラハム
Raham.
先が全然見えないな
あるのはがれきの山だ
We’ll never finish this work.
It’s nothing but rubble.
頑張っていれば何とかなるさ
At least we’re trying to make a change.
のんきなもんだな
Always an optimist.
By the way, you’re late on your rent
そういえば 家賃まだだよな
またか？
—again.
Raham, I’m sorry;
ラハム すまない
I need more time.
もう少し待ってくれ
城壁の仕事が・・・
With the work on the wall, . . .
I have enough troubles.
こっちもいろいろ大変なんだ
Look, if I don’t get payment
月末までに払えないなら
出ていってもらう
by the end of the month,
you and your family are out.
Is there anything we can do?
何でもするよ
Maybe I can work it off till we get caught up.
何かないかな
必ず払うから
おまえにはこれ以上無理だろ
Seriously?
You don’t have time to work it off,
でもおまえの娘が
うちで働いてくれたら・・・
but maybe your daughter can help.
She can come stay with us.
奴隷になれって？
As a slave?
No, I’ll hire her to help Azubah
そうじゃない アズバの手伝いだ
—to pay off your debt.
それで何とかしてやるよ
Look, I’m trying to help,
but you don’t have many options here, my friend.
断れる身分か？
Think about it.
よく考えろ
So Raham spoke to me today.
今日 ラハムに言われたんだけど
About what?
何を？
シムカに家に来てもらいたいって
アズバの手伝い
He wants to hire Simcha to help Azubah in the house.
He says he’ll care for her like his own daughter.
わが子のように世話するって
それに あの夫婦はエズラと一緒に
ここに来た時からの付き合いだ
Imma, I’ve known Raham and Azubah
ever since I came here with Ezra.
Raham helped us.
世話になってるし
この家も借りてる
Our house belongs to him.
あの人信じられる？
I don’t trust him.
He wants our Simcha to live with him?
シムカを預けるなんて・・・
あり得ない！
Imma, . . .
あー
What about Jehovah’s command
親が自分の子供を育てるという
エホバの命令はどうなるの？
that parents raise their own children?
楽させてやりたいだろ？
Don’t you want her to have a better life?
I-I cannot agree
私は・・・ 私は嫌だわ
離れて暮らすなんて
to having her live apart from us,
たとえ食べる物に困ったとしても
even if we have to survive on gleanings.
じゃあ どうすればいいんだ？
How do you know we’ll survive at all?
Because Jehovah always takes care
エホバはご自分に愛と従順を
示す者たちを見捨てないでしょ
of those who love and obey him.
Men like Peleth threw their burden on Jehovah
ペレトのような人たちは重荷を
エホバに委ね 仕事を続けました
and kept working.
サンバラテは エルサレムの近くに
テントを張って
Sanballat set up camp near Jerusalem
to keep an eye on our progress.
私たちの行動を見張っていました
So, what is it?
どうだった？
My lord.
はい
うん？
Yes?
The wall
城壁は 半分ほど出来上がりました
—it’s up to half its height all around the city.
This has gone too far!
それはまずいな
Geshem, how long will it take
ゲシェム 攻撃の準備に
どれくらいかかる？
to assemble an attack force?
Attack force?
攻撃ですか
My lord, Sanballat, an attack on the Jews
サンバラテ ユダを攻めるのは
ペルシャを敵に回すということですよ
would be an attack on the king.
どういう意味だ？
What are you talking about?
彼の言う通りです ネヘミヤには
アルタクセルクセスが付いています
He’s right.
Nehemiah has authorization from Artaxerxes himself.
どれだけの兵士が
一緒に送り込まれたか！
You saw how many horsemen the king sent with him.
Yes!
その兵士がこの近くにいたとしたら
Would you be talking like this if those horsemen
were still here?
いつでも攻撃される
And they can come back.
Nonsense!
ばかげてる！兵士は関係ない
Never mind the horsemen.
This is my province!
ここは私の領地だ
Out here, I decide what to do.
何をするかは私が決める
いいか やつらを脅すんだ
Now, we need to threaten them.
Geshem, you bring Samaritan troops
ゲシェム サマリアの軍隊を
このルートで連れて来てくれ
and come in from this way.
やつらは攻撃の準備をしてる！
They’re preparing to attack us!
どこで聞いたんですか？
How do you know that?
I heard them talking.
みんなそう言ってる
皆さん落ち着いてください
もう攻めてきたんですか？
Brothers, please.
Have they attacked anyone yet?
来てるはずだ！彼なら知ってる
They must have.
He saw something.
Are you going to wait until they start killing us?
殺されるまで待ってろと言うのですか？
Of course not!
いや そんなことにはならない！
Hanani,
ハナニ
post men by families at the lowest parts of the wall
家族ごとに人を出して城壁の
まだふさがれていない部分を守ろう
—at all the exposed places.
分かりました
Yes, Nehemiah.
That’s not going to work.
うまくいきっこない
Brothers,
皆さん 再建をやめたら
敵の思うつぼです
if we let mere threats frighten us into stopping,
they will have achieved their goal.
やつらは俺たちのやってることが
気に食わないんだ 分からないんですか
It’s no use. Don’t you see?
These people hate what we’re doing.
They hate us.
何も知らないくせに！
You don’t have to live and work around them like we do.
Brothers,
兄弟たち 信仰を強めましょう！
where is your faith?
エホバは城壁の再建を望んでおられます
It is Jehovah’s will that we build this wall.
If it is really Jehovah’s will,
それが本当なら どうして
こんな目に遭うんだ？
then why are we getting all this opposition?
まだその時じゃないんだ
Maybe this isn’t the right time.
それに仕事が多過ぎる もうへとへとだ
Besides, this work is too much for us.
We’re worn out.
Why do we need a wall anyway?
そもそも何で城壁が必要なんだ？
エホバの民を守るためです
To protect Jehovah’s people.
Brothers,
兄弟たち
do not be afraid of them.
彼らのことを恐れてはなりません
Remember Jehovah,
偉大で威厳に満ちるエホバが
おられることを忘れないでください
who is great and awe-inspiring;
and fight for your brothers,
兄弟たちのため
your sons and daughters,
息子や娘のため
妻 そして家のために戦いなさい
your wives and homes.
So when you hear the sound of the horn,
角笛の音を聞いたら
私の所に集合しなさい
gather together to where we are.
神が私たちのために戦ってくださいます
Our God will fight for us.
角笛の音が合図です
Listen for this signal.
The threats aren’t working.
脅しは効かなかった
The next sound they hear will be our battle cry.
こうなったら攻め込むしかないだろう
Wait!
待ってください！
前にも話した通り
We already spoke about this.
A direct attack would be seditious.
手を出したら負けです
Besides, they’ve armed themselves.
それに向こうも武装しています
Wait!
落ち着いてください！ 主よ
My-my lord,
Geshem is right.
ゲシェムの言う通りです
攻撃すべきではありません
We’d never get away with this.
誰がネヘミヤを送り込んだか
ご存じですね
Don’t you recall who commissioned Nehemiah?
It was the king.
王です ペルシャの王です
It was the king of Persia, let me remind you.
いいですね
Nehemiah is setting himself up as a king.
ネヘミヤは権力が欲しいだけだ
いい考えがあります
I recommend we turn the accusation of sedition
ネヘミヤを反逆の罪で
訴えるのはどうでしょう
against Nehemiah.
それはいい
That’s brilliant!
Yes,
なるほど その手があるな
ネヘミヤを追い込んでやる
he will beg for our help.
Let’s go back to Samaria.
よしサマリアに戻ろう
ハナニ
Hanani,
you look like you’ve been working.
板についてきたな
I must smell like it too.
結構汗臭いでしょ
Yes!
お互いさまだね
Yes, you do.
Brothers!
兄弟たち！
Brothers, we are well on our way to completing the wall.
作業は順調で完成間近です
Jehovah is helping us,
エホバは助けてくださっています
but we must not let our hands drop.
もう少しです 頑張りましょう
From now on,
今日からエルサレムの中で
夜を過ごすことにします
we will all spend the night inside Jerusalem.
We will take turns keeping watch.
交代で見張りをしましょう
Hanani will give out assignments.
ハナニが順番を決めてくれます
Good work today.
よろしくお願いします
みんな城壁の再建に打ち込みました
Everyone was working hard on the wall.
しかし ほかにも難しい
問題がありました
But there were more issues to contend with.
兄弟たち
My brothers, how can I help you?
何かありましたか
Nehemiah, we, with our sons and daughters, are many.
ネヘミヤ うちには
子供がたくさんいます
We need food to stay alive.
食糧が必要なんです
We gave our fields and vineyards
食糧を買うために畑やブドウ園
and houses as security to get grain during
それに家も担保に入れました
the food shortage.
We borrowed money
税金を払うため 畑とブドウ園を
担保にしてお金を借りました
on our fields and our vineyards to pay the king’s tribute.
子供を奴隷として売った人もいます
And we’ve had to sell some of our children into slavery.
We’re powerless to stop this
何もかも人手に渡ってしまったので
もうどうしようもないんです
because our fields and vineyards belong to others.
Thank you for bringing this to my attention.
分かりました 何とかします
I must ponder all this.
ありがとうございます
Thank you, Nehemiah.
Thank you.
ハナニ 町の有力者たちに
明日の朝集まるように伝えてください
Hanani, please tell all the nobles
and deputy rulers to come to me
first thing tomorrow morning.
問題を解決できるよう
エホバが助けてくださるでしょう
With God’s help, we can make this right.
Men of Judah,
ユダ族の皆さん
each of you is demanding interest from your brother.
皆さんは兄弟たちから
利息を取ってお金を貸しています
You should be ashamed of yourselves.
恥ずかしくないのですか
Should you not walk in the fear of our God
周りの民族や敵から非難されないよう
so that the nations, our enemies,
何事も神を畏れつつ
行うべきではないでしょうか
cannot reproach us?
Let us, please, stop this lending on interest.
どうか利息を取るのはやめてください
彼らの畑 ブドウ園
オリーブ畑 家を返し
Please restore to them their fields,
vineyards, olive groves, houses,
利息を返してあげてください
and the interest.
Nehemiah, I will restore the fields this day at sunset.
分かりました ネヘミヤ
夕方までに畑を全て返します
言われた通り全て兄弟たちに返します
We all will restore these things to our brothers.
Before Jehovah,
エホバの前で 約束を
守ることを誓いますか
do you swear to these promises?
We do!
誓います！
May the true God shake out from his house
約束を守らない人は真の神によって
every man who does not carry out this promise.
自分の家から放り出されますように
Amen!
アーメン！
Meshullam,
メシュラム
we must inform Tobiah about this.
このことをトビヤに知らせないと
This will be successful.
大丈夫 うまくいく
エホバは祝福してくださる
Jehovah will bless it.
ラハム！
Raham!
I bring good news.
いい知らせだ
Is that so?
あ そう
Yes.
そう
We have your rent.
家賃が払える
Oh?
えっ？
Come by anytime and collect it.
いつ取りに来てもいいよ
But I thought we—
でも シムカはどうなった？
What about Simcha?
She’ll be staying with us.
僕たちと一緒にいる
どうしてこんなに早く返せるんだ？
Well, how were you able to put it together so quickly?
エホバはご自分に愛と従順を
示す者たちを見捨てない
Jehovah always takes care of those
who love and obey him.
Ever since Nehemiah got here,
ネヘミヤが来てから
状況はどんどん良くなってる
things have been getting better and better.
Nehemiah thinks we’re still as young
ネヘミヤは俺たちが
まだ若いと思っている
as when we came here with Ezra.
I’ve worked hard.
俺は一生懸命働いてきた
なのにネヘミヤは何でも
天から降って来ると思っている
But now Nehemiah treats us like it all fell out of heaven,
and we just have to pick it up.
I worked hard for what I have, didn’t I?
全部俺が稼いだ！そうだろ
あなたには感謝してる
Yes, you worked hard.
If I give back my fields,
言われた通り土地を返してみろ
what am I to eat?
どうなる どうやって食っていくんだ！
What am I to drink?
利息を取ることのどこがいけないんだ？
What’s wrong with lending on interest?
You borrow, you pay with interest.
金を貸したら 利息を取る
エホバは 兄弟たちを公正に扱うよう
望んでるんじゃないかしら
Raham, Jehovah just wants us
to treat our brothers fairly, doesn’t he?
どういうことだ 俺はみんなを
公正に扱ってきた
Haven’t you heard a word I said?
I treat everyone fairly!
どうしてそんなに怒ってるの？
Then why are you so angry?
怒ってなんかいない
I’m not angry!
じゃ なんでそんな言い方するの？
Why are you talking to me like this?
I just feel betrayed.
裏切られた気分なんだ
誰に？
By whom?
By the people I’ve lent money to!
金を貸したやつらにさ！
私に何かできる？
What can I do about it?
Only what a wife is supposed to do!
女の務めを果たせ 息子を産むんだ
Give me a son!
If not a son, then a daughter.
駄目なら娘でもいい
むちゃ言わないで
子供はエホバからの贈り物よ
I cannot give you what Jehovah does not give us.
One day,
いつまでも待てないからな！
it will be too late.
王に書簡を送りましょう
I say we write a letter to the king.
そうか じゃああいつの報告を待とう
Well, let’s see what the boy reports when he returns.
My lord, Sanballat.
主よ
Now what?
遅かったな
The wall has no more gaps.
間もなく城壁が完成します
What?
何だと？
なぜだ 早過ぎるだろ
How can they advance so quickly?
Also, there’s a letter for Tobiah.
それとトビヤ宛ての書簡です
Nehemiah is forcing
ネヘミヤは 土地を元の
持ち主に返すよう
landlords to return their fields to the original owners.
圧力をかけてきました
もう時間がない
We’re running out of time.
もういい
Enough!
Tell this to Nehemiah:
ネヘミヤにこう伝えろ
“Come, and let us set a time
「オノの谷あいの平原の村で会おう」
to meet together in the Valley Plain of Ono.”
They’re trying to lure me away from Jerusalem
私をエルサレムからおびき出すつもりだ
to do me harm.
Please, tell your master:
こう伝えなさい
“I am engaged in a great work,
「いま大きな仕事をしているので
行けません
“and I am not able to go down.
あなた方の所に行くと
仕事が止まってしまいます」
“Why should the work stop
while I leave it to come to you?”
They sent me the same message several times.
彼らは何度も同じことを言ってきました
そのたびに 私も同じ返事をしました
Each time I gave them the same response.
主よ 彼は4回も断ってきました
My lord, he has rejected your offer a fourth time.
ゲシェム あの手で行くしかないな
Geshem,
it’s time to implement your plan.
Tobiah,
トビヤ 書いてくれ
write this down:
“Among the nations it has been heard,
「周りの民族の間であなたのことが
うわさになっている
“and Geshem is also saying it,
ゲシェムも言っていたが
“that you and the Jews
あなたとユダヤ人は
反逆をもくろんでいる
“are scheming to rebel.
That is why you are building the wall.”
だから城壁を建て直している」
Yes?
どうした
ネヘミヤにこれを
Give this to Nehemiah.
Tell your master:
こう伝えなさい
“None of the things you are saying have taken place.
「あなたが言っているのは
本当のことではありません
You are making them up out of your own imagination.”
あなたが勝手に考えたことです」
They’re bluffing.
心配するな
動揺させて作業を
やめさせようとしているだけだ
They’re trying to frighten us into stopping the work.
Yes, they know that the king won’t change his decree.
城壁再建が王の命令だと知ってるのに
反対し続けてる
But believe me, they won’t stop.
やめようとしない
Jehovah, I pray,
エホバ
どうか強めてください 私の手を
strengthen my hands.
What can we do to stop him?
われわれは今何をすべきだろうか
もう時間がない
We don’t have much time.
The wall is almost complete.
間もなく城壁は完成してしまう
Sanballat,
サンバラテ
私に考えがあります
I think I know a way.
シェマヤ
何かありましたか
Shemaiah, you called for me.
Yes!
はい
Quickly!
入って！
You are in great danger.
危険が迫ってる
大変なことになるぞ
And so am I because I know about it.
Talk sense, man!
落ち着け！何のことだ？
What danger?
They’re coming to kill you—by night!
やつらが殺しに来る 今夜だ！
We must go into the temple and close the doors.
神殿に逃げ込んで 扉を閉めるんだ
Shemaiah,
シェマヤ 総督である私が逃げるのか？
should a man like me run away?
そんなこと言ってる場合じゃない
You don’t understand.
いや 私がそんなことをしたら
みんなはどう思う？
What would that do to the spirit of the entire nation?
安全な場所はそこしかない
It’s the only safe place.
それに 私は祭司でもない
Besides, I’m not a priest.
If I entered the temple,
神殿に入ることは許されていない
that would be valid reason to kill me.
I will not go in.
私は入らない！
That decision would be foolish, Nehemiah.
俺の言う通りにするんだ
Oh, I see!
そうか
Tobiah and Sanballat put you up to this,
トビヤとサンバラテの差し金か
didn’t they, you hypocrite?
この裏切り者！
May Jehovah remember them
エホバは 敵たちと あなた方
偽預言者たちを処罰される
and all of you false prophets
who keep trying to frighten me.
Come, Hanani,
行こうハナニ 仕事に戻ろう
we have work to do.
Argh!
うわーっ！
We just kept working day and night.
私たちは昼も夜も働き続けました
But before we knew it,
そしてついに 修復は
最後の部分を迎えます
we were finishing the very last section of the wall.
エホバは不可能を可能に
してくださいました
Jehovah helped us to achieve the impossible.
体は疲れていましたが
We were tired,
それを補って余りあるものがありました
but we discovered something we had lost
そう 「喜び」です
—joy.
Nehemiah, the wall is complete!
ネヘミヤ ついに完成だ！
Yeah! Yes!
やった！終わったぞ！
That’s it.
よくやったな！
たった52日ですよ
In just 52 days.
My lord, it’s from Shemaiah.
シェマヤからです
What does it say?
何て言ってます？
The wall is complete.
城壁は完成した・・・
Only the doors are left to be put in.
あとは扉を付けるだけだ
Sanballat, we must act quickly.
サンバラテ 急がないと
サンバラテ・・・
Sanballat . . .
やめろ トビヤ
Stop it, Tobiah.
No, there’s still time.
まだ時間はある あの手紙を王に送ろう
Write that letter to the king.
Tobiah,
トビヤ 分からないのか
don’t you see?
God must be helping the Jews.
神がユダヤ人を助けた
It’s over.
もう終わったんだ
We’ll lose all control over them.
終わったわけではない
This isn’t over.
まだ何とかなる
城壁の再建はほんの始まりに
すぎませんでした
Rebuilding the walls was only the beginning.
エホバの助けが本当に必要になるのは
We would definitely need God’s help
for what was coming next.
これからでした